Intoxication is the nature of the moon
May 10th is a special pournami are a special full moon day because it's called Buddha Pournami
this is the day Gautama the buddha got enlightened
you notice
This year it's on 10th of may this full moon day is the day gautama the buddha got enlightened
There are many aspects to his life
The most important aspect is that he is a Bhu-dda
That's not his name
His name is Gautama Siddhartha, but he is a Buddha
Buddha means he transcended his intellect
Bhu means Buddhi
Dha means Datha
Buddhi means the intellect datha means one who is above one who is above his intellect is a buddha
One who is in his intellect is a non-stop suffering human being
Something happens they suffer nothing happens they suffer whichever way
that is if you're below the mind we call them Buddhu
If you are above the mind you are a buddha if you're below the mind you are Buddhu if you are in the mind
are nonstop suffering
So, how did you become this?
He tried many things in his life. He was a prince of a small princely state
because
some
yogi predicted that this will either become a great emperor or
become a great sage
when you made this prediction the father got
little
excited. he did not want him to become a great sage. He wanted to become a great emperor
So he decided he will not expose him to because he thought by
Being exposed to some suffering or misery he may turn into usage
So he kept him in utter pleasure... the best of food, best of clothes, best of pleasures, everything
When he was a 19 years of age he got him married to a very pretty young woman
kept him in a palace secluded from the rest of the society
Where he lives in pleasure never exposed to any kind of suffering.
One day he thought he will just take a drive through the town he asked his charioter to take him across
So he was going and then he saw a man who was old.
Was going like this
So he had never seen old man in his life his father had protected him from all this
See what has happened to him, so the charioter said that's just an old man
How does it happen he asked?
Said everybody gets old some day
He looked at himself use a nice youth
What me also?
Said yes, everybody everybody gets old
they live long enough they get old
You this was a realization for him. I will become like this
Then he saw a man lying on the street was ill with something
Not able to get up in great suffering. He said stop. What is this guy? What's he doing?
He said oh, he's sick unfortunately
What does that mean?
He said my body sometimes it gets sick
It can happen to anybody it can happen to just anybody me a prince
Can happen to me it can happen to anybody?
And he's how I can become like this
Then they were going further. He was completely disturbed by this then he saw a funeral they were carrying a
Dead body of A man
What happened to that guy? Oh he just died?
What does that mean? that happens to everybody without exception?
Then he said what am I doing just eating pleasures nonsense? What am I doing with myself and
He struggled he went into turmoil within himself
This suddenly being a prince and his pleasures and all this palace
Suddenly broke apart for him and he started looking
What is the point of all this this is going to get old this may get sick for sure this will be dead?
What am I investing my entire life in this?
But by then he had an infant boy
he looked at his wife and
his child
this
Loving wife and this lovely little baby. He could not leave he struggled and struggled and struggled
By then a little or one and a quarter years passed
when the boy was one and a half years of age
He could not hold it anymore in the middle of the night like a thief
Without telling anybody he slipped out of the palace and left for good
He went in search. I want to know the truth about this life
He went from school to school
These are times when different schools were established in India
At one point there were over
1,800 schools, I'm saying not just institutions
1800 different ways of doing things
[1800] different varieties [of] Yoga
Not the kind that you're seeing in
Somebody doing like this somebody doing like this really intricate
Expressions, it is like how the medical science is becoming today
25 years ago you wanted a medical check-up. All you needed was your family doctor
today
But every part of your body there [is] a doctor I
Was [a] Few years ago. I had
You know I had a knee injury. I was playing soccer, and I broke something in the knee and
I was all packed up, and I was speaking
That's how I got into golf
Because of this knee injury
Somebody told me gifted me of golf kit and said Sadhguru, you're too old for any other game. You just play golf
So I was sitting [there] in Atlanta talking speaking at a place
Then I was in pain, I couldn't even move
so
After the when this is over. I mean when I was speaking one person raised his hand I thought he wants a question
But then he said Sadhguru, I would like to examine your knee after
The zoa, I [am] a knee doctor. I
Said come on. You are not to panic [so] [no] no I am a new doctor
Then I said right or left
Which one are you?
so
specialization
Specialization is going a time will come probably in 50 years time if you want a medical check-up
You need 100 doctors to check you by the time you get these 100 appointments
Maybe you need an undertaker
Then it will become ridiculous. Okay, you went to three doctors. All right you and do
Five doctors all right if it becomes fifty [hundred] doctors for a medical check-up
It's become ridiculous. Isn't it this happened to yogic system
People started specializing and specializing in variety of small things
Each specialization has a whole thing by [itself]
Someone just came and told me [they're] a dentist okay. [I'm] not speaking in another thing for example dentistry just 32 teeth
Right they study for nine Years
[Thirty-Two] teeth
Nine years of study still they don't know everything about it. That's the nature of creation
If you start studying one tooth at a time, you will see each one of them has something specific about it
You somebody can spend a lifetime of study just learning about one tooth
Just see if you had 32 dentists to look at your mouth
Disaster you are isn't it so a specialization?
Specialization happens when it crosses a certain point it will become ridiculous this happened to yoga it
crossed that point where
[1800] schools different specializations of Yoga happened
So that is when patanjali came and kind of assimilated everything into yoga Sutras to minimize this expanse
That was growing endlessly
so when Gothama came it was post patanjali, but
Still there were many things so he went from school to school
He pursued eight different forms of Samadhi
We talk about [semantics], okay?
He saw all of them were wonderful experiences, but still it did not liberate him
so in this condition
He was walking as a samana. There's a certain system of
practice called Samanas their fundamental practices this
They will never ask for food
You should not go in pursuit of food
because
they want to beat the
fundamental Instinct of survival
No matter what you're always going in pursuit of food, please understand this you may complicate it in so many ways, but fundamentally
You're talking so much the word economy means you're just thinking about survival all the time isn't it
[sir], I will glorify it, but till it is survival
So one fundamental Sadhana for them is you never pursue your instinct of survival
You simply keep going so samanas used to just walk
never asking for food
but the culture was sensitive if they saw a spiritual person walking people will cook at home and run behind him and
serve him wherever he is
Because they know he will not ask for food
Today if you become a samana you will walk yourself to death
Those days people were sensitive to his sadhana and responded so there were thousands of samanas walking the country
so Gotham on became a samana and
Even if you are not asking for food, you will walk near a town
so the food will come
but Gothama took it too seriously and
Just walked he became all bones
just
bones and a bag of skin like that he became
Then he came to a place where there was a river called Niranjana unfortunately that river is gone now
no, more river
just
About 18 to 20 inches of water may be moving little rapidly
He stepped into it halfway down into the river. He did not have the energy to cross
There was a tree branch a dead branch he just held onto it
He doesn't have the strength to take the next step
But he's not the kind of man to let go he held on we don't know for how long
People say for a very long time maybe it was two minutes
When you're feeling, so weak those two minutes might have looked like
many years
Then as he hung on
He just realized what is it that? I'm striving for
What is it I'm wondering the entire country growing from school to school learning this learning that what is it that? I'm looking for
Then he realized
This is really nothing
This life is wrong. All I have to do is
Just take away the barriers which are not allowing me to experience this
When he realized that everything is within him. There's nowhere to search
Suddenly he had the energy to take the next step in the next step across the river came and sat down under that
Now very famous bodhi tree
Which has become more then the buddha himself?
A
part of the tree a remnant Or a progeny of the tree still exists in both Gaya
and
He sat under the tree. It was this full moon night. Which is coming now
on 10th of May
He sat there, and he sat there with this determination either
I must see the ultimate nature of my existence now
Or I will sit here and die I will not open my eyes till I know this
Once he made that resolve because the only problem is there is no resolve every two minutes your intentions are changing
If you are totally on to know, what is within you how long should it take?
It should happen in a moment, isn't [it]?
Because there is no distance to travel
Time is a quantity which [is] necessary only when there is a distance to travel isn't it?
If there is no distance to travel if I ask you, how long does it take for you [to] sit [here]?
You're already sitting
It's already there. It doesn't take any time
So you're already alive and on it doesn't take any time for realization because you don't have to do anything particularly?
when he saw this he was fully enlightened and the moon was shining and
He had not eaten for many months on end properly used actually for years. He was a samana and
People around him he had gathered about five disciples. I think
These guys thought he's real because he doesn't eat his really rigid
and
They saw he's in some state exuberant state and they could see the light on his face
Then they were waiting for him to open his eyes and give the teaching
He opened his eyes look them smiled and said cook something let's eat
They have a totally disappointed they thought he has lost it
They walked with him for four to eight years
when he had nothing, but torture
When he got enlightened they left him
because
They wanted to hear something severe
He said cook something let's eat
We've been wasting our time
There are many beautiful episodes in his life
When he one day walked upon the Riverbank after he has become a good and went and sat down under a tree
Tree not because tree is the best place to sit under you know ants can get you
Because that was the only real estate of those times there are no buildings and buildings and buildings everywhere
So tree was a good place to a pleasant place to sit under rather than sitting in harsh sun. You sit under a tree
An astrologer who is of great
proficiency in history
Saw the footprint on the Riverbank he had come to
In the in India people of any this thing means bad means always river those rivers are going away. I will tell you later
bath means always river
So he came for a bath that they were then he saw the footprint
There is a whole science
or
rather
observations
Through which by looking at the way [one's] feet is somebody predicts exactly what he will do
So he saw the footprint and then he saw that this is the footprint of an emperor somebody who should rule the world
Then he wondered why would such a person be in this remote place near the jungle
Then he followed the footprint
Thinking he will meet an emperor
Then he saw this monk
Gothama sitting under a tree
Then he looked at this this he thought either my astrology has gone all wrong
or I am being fooled or and in some kind of a hallucination
What's happening here then he went to Gotham and asked who are you?
Gautama was in this kind of just Jeet kind of state
He said and no crime. [I] am just a nobody
But you have the feet of an emperor you should conquer the world
Gautama said that I will
But not by conquest see there are two ways you can have the world either by conquest or by inclusion
yes, I
can make you yours either by capturing you chaining you and making you do what I want or
By including you as a part of myself. Yes
Both ways something or somebody becomes yours isn't it
But if you go by conquest, it will be a pain in your neck always
if you include
This will become a great enhancement of life
He said I am the emperor of the world, but then he said you're a monk you own  nothing.
I own nothing and I am a nobody that is why?
Everything is mine
Even mathematicians are trying to teach you the zero on the infinite or one and the same
So you becoming of a no thing?
does not mean
You are of no use
You are [a] no thing means you have  become
All inclusive, isn't it you're something means you can only be that
You're nothing you can be any way you want this is how this life is made if your ability to respond is not curtailed
You can be anything you wish at any given moment, isn't it?
So Gothama said I am  anyway the emperor of the world if that's the word you like, but I'm actually a nobody
Because everything is anyway mine
If you see, I'm responsible for everything everything is yours isn't it how does somebody become yours
Because you want them or you take responsibility for that?
because you take [responsibility] [for] them they become yours not otherwise, isn't it
If you own them forcefully they will never be yours
Yes, or no if you forcefully own
somebody will they ever be yours they'll never ever be yours
So this astrologer sat down
They said you're a monk you have nothing on top of it. You say you're just it. I'm sorry
I'm top of it you say I'm a nobody and
Everything is yours. What is this?
Gothama said you come I have a way for you
You are busy making predictions of Life
I have a plan
Why do you make predictions of life?
[you're] incapable of making a plan and executing a plan that is why you fall back any predictions isn't it?
if you are capable of making a plan and executing the plan would you fall back on predictions?
no
So gautama said you were busy making predictions. I'm here. I have a plan
Come become a part of my plan
We'll make something else happen
You must become a part of this plan we can make something wonderful happen
this same world
This same World can be turned into paradise
If all its all of us, go buy a paradise plan isn't it?
Yes, or no
The question is only
do that because between a
Possibility, and the reality there is a distance or do we have the courage and the commitment to walk the distance. That's all it is
Yes
you