I
Was just
Talking to somebody who's some kind of an expert on the internet and stuff. I said what's happening because I?
Don't get to see anything except a bit of nails and our own work
all the time I
Never get to browse or see anything so I was asking what are people looking for what is it?
And he's saying it like it's a matter of fact. He's saying that it was 70% his only pornography
70% of
The Internet traffic is pornography. I don't know if this percentage is correct, but if it's anywhere near that I
Mean what's happened to us
When such a powerful medium that we can communicate with the entire world don't we have anything better to say
I'm not trying to be moralistic and said this is wrong
That is wrong, but I am saying for the first time
In the history of humanity we have this capability
That we can
Say something to the entire world in one shot
Never before this was even imaginable. Isn't it I?
Want you to understand you just taken it for granted your whatever?
Instagrams and what's apps and Twitter's and emails don't take it for granted. This is the first time?
That we can communicate
to every human being on the planet
Is it not important the highest possibilities get to them?
Today
the three
biggest industries on the planet are the first number-one industries arms and armaments
Number two is alcohol and tobacco put together
Number three is for Monsieur tickles
This says everything about us. What kind of people we are isn't it and
On the Internet is pornography
We as a generation should not let this opportunity pass we should not let these
Sex maniacs
Child sellers to dominate this world
How can we allow people who sell children to do dirty things with them to dominate this planet?
Tell me we are allowing them to do it
We don't have to fight them everybody thinks we have to fight no we have to overwhelm them with positive things
You